[SPEAKER_01]: So, one of the questions that people who come to the hermitage ask most frequently,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a particular order?
[SPEAKER_01]: And are certain discourses more suitable to begin with than others?
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if someone asks you a question like that, then how would you reply?
[SPEAKER_03]: To give a very technical answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: One thing worth mentioning is that the Dīgha Nikaya has the... by proportion, it has the most suttas addressed to householders.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is one consideration.
[SPEAKER_03]: Though maybe not the most important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what will be, to your mind, the most important consideration?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it depends what people are coming to the practice for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oftentimes, the
[SPEAKER_03]: The starting point that at least I had, the reasons I became interested in the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_03]: I've learned need to change over time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: For me, just reading as many as possible, and kind of getting a taste for what they were,
[SPEAKER_03]: Others may not have so much of a...
[SPEAKER_03]: But others might not need that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, depending on people's preclivities, that would be...
[SPEAKER_03]: worth taking into account.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, of course, the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Something worth mentioning is that, in the suttas, there's this distinction between people who have right view and those who don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, perhaps, explaining some of the indications...
[SPEAKER_03]: In the suttas, that might let you know, oh, is this addressed to somebody with or without right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to be clear about this, the discourses are records of conversations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: People approaching the Buddha and other awakened beings and asking them
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is there a single discourse where two people who do not have the right view are having a conversation?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the chief value of the discourses then, to start with, is that there's always at least a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: or else an arahant appearing on the scene, in order to clarify certain matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is why the collection of Nikayas stand out from other writings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, it would just be a collection of ordinary conversations and that doesn't really go anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, then there is the possibility that noble ones are giving instructions to those who do not yet have a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, there's the possibility that no one's having a conversation among themselves, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you are saying that it is good to keep in mind that there is a distinction between those who have a right view and those who do not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, how is a newcomer...
[SPEAKER_01]: who is about to dive into the discourses, going to find out whether there is a conversation between two noble ones or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why should that matter?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the attitude of someone who's approaching the discourses, now that we have introduced this distinction?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's also a matter of becoming clear what is rightful and not, and
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's a very wide, very open discussion, since eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: It can be discussed over this matter for a long time without having a
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a common point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Depending, depending on how one can read the texts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all this maybe has to be mentioned.
[SPEAKER_02]: The the text can be
[SPEAKER_02]: The parikāna can be read or interpreted in different ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, each way, pretending to have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the end, someone needs to check within their own experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means what?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is, let's go one step back, what is the attitude of someone who approaches the discourses?
[SPEAKER_00]: If they are coming to it for the first time, yeah, well, that they...
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, you're talking about two noble ones having a conversation.
[SPEAKER_00]: They shouldn't assume that they are in a position to
[SPEAKER_00]: Understand what is being spoken about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they shouldn't assume that this applies to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, you know, ānāpānasati, or these satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a fatal error to assume that what I am reading, my interpretation of what is being written,
[SPEAKER_00]: is correct, and that I have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm in a position to practice now, because that is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Undermining your ability to question the assumptions that you're bringing to this interpretation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if someone already assumes...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if someone assumes that all the discourses are on the same level...
[SPEAKER_01]: So to speak, that they equally apply to everyone, and that those instructions, and those teachings, and those contemplations, that they can at once
[SPEAKER_01]: Put that into practice and obscure the fact that the right view is something to be acquired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by making some big donation, or by performing an esoteric ceremony of some sort, but by understanding these four Noble Truths directly for oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that is overlooked...
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there's actually an obstacle for coming to see the dhamma, if somebody thinks they have already understood what has in fact not been understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it will prevent them from understanding what needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the attitude has to be what?
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude is, I am reading a text and I don't yet know what this is about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, reading a text, then, is a... it's not about accumulating information, but about questioning one's own views and assumptions, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Checking whether that is in accordance with the with the noble views that are expressed in the discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are we going to say all this to people who come here and ask where to begin with reading the Discourses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that is what we should be saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if we have introduced this distinction between those who are of a right view
[SPEAKER_01]: And those who are not?
[SPEAKER_01]: And we see that it is important to start out by saying one doesn't have right view and so this is something to acquire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose somebody accepts that, and then they're going to read the discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what's the next thing they should be looking for?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, your question from a little bit earlier about how do you know what the context is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this two noble disciples or...?
[SPEAKER_03]: One noble disciple, one ordinary person.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you know?
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: What comes to mind for that is usually if it's addressed to monks, and it just kind of leaves it at that.
[SPEAKER_03]: No other elaboration.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's generally... that's generally a conversation between noble disciples, or the Buddha addressing them, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: That, that's a good implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the discourses, conversation between monks are nine out of ten times between those who are already of right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nowadays the situation is different, but if somebody is studying the discourses, there's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, can we say anything more than this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometimes I'll just flip to the end of a sutta before reading it, just kind of see how it plays out, because sometimes it is like, oh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Magnificent.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, when it says, the dhamma-I arose, that means that at the beginning of the conversation...
[SPEAKER_03]: They didn't have right view, but at the end, they acquired it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, those are pretty valuable suttas, because that's like, okay, this is addressed to somebody...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there are a number of discourses you are saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: where somebody actually breaks through, so to speak, to the right understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if we have agreed that
[SPEAKER_01]: If newcomers are not yet of the right view, then those are the kinds of discourses they want to be looking into first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And understand those first, because there's valuable clues there, as to what leads to seeing the dhamma directly for oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Those discourses where somebody actually breaks through to the right understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one kind of discourse.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are a dozen or two such discourses in the Nikayas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, is there another type of discourse that is
[SPEAKER_01]: On that same level, so to speak, a kind of stock phrase that frequently appears in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_01]: That people who are new should be looking out for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, although, yeah, yeah, yeah, that's actually true.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's also this thought phrase where it says here, an untold ordinary person...
[SPEAKER_01]: who has no regard for noble ones, and has not known and seen the dhamma, regards things, and then there comes a description.
[SPEAKER_01]: of how people who are not of the right view are regarding things, whether it be aggregates or sense bases or other aspects of their experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is then contrasted with how a well-instructed noble disciple, who knows and sees the dhamma, regards things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are quite a number of those.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's often a stock phrase.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's another set of discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which directly contrasts the understanding between those who are not in the right view and those who are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, are we saying that it would be good for somebody who wants to find access into the discourses to start looking for those as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I haven't thought about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's probably a good way to approach it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think, inevitably, there's going to be, even in that, in that approach,
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's just very important to say that it's incredibly difficult to...
[SPEAKER_00]: To really... with with all of the views that
[SPEAKER_00]: The sutras that are so prominent today, the scientific view, the religious views, yeah, the sutras are so broad.
[SPEAKER_00]: In their phenomenological descriptions, that it's incredibly difficult to...
[SPEAKER_00]: To see what they're saying, in a sense, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, I mean, you can you can say, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now that we've given some indications that are different kinds of discourses, that's what we said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where someone gains the right view and these stock phrases you were just talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suppose we leave that for now and we're going to discuss somebody's attitude towards those discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you just mentioned scientific view and religious view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if somebody is a scholar,
[SPEAKER_01]: or an academic, and they are concerned with writing papers, and they happen to take an interest in early Buddhism,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, it's publish or perish.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, there's pressure to put material out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uhm, if that's their background attitude towards reading those discourses, then is that practically gonna make any...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the difference for them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are they going to gain the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so they're coming to the text with that context, which is obviously not a wholesome one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the publish or perish attitude, for example, there's obviously craving involved in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or financial incentives or whatever, but that's putting that aside, even if those weren't there.
[SPEAKER_00]: To approach it in a scholarly way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not... the suttas are...
[SPEAKER_00]: They require authenticity, self-transparency.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, that's, you know, that's what the precepts are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can we make explicit what is then the difference between what we now call a scholarly attitude and an authentic attitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why is a scholarly attitude not going to be beneficial in terms of
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the goal of the real practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the obstacle there?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's not seen in that attitude?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's horizontal.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the approach of taking in
[SPEAKER_02]: A lot of information, and then using it to build up...
[SPEAKER_02]: Argumentations or...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, this could bring up explanations.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a sense of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, putting one one notion after the other, whereas the
[SPEAKER_02]: The authentic, if I'm right, as you call it, approaches.
[SPEAKER_02]: To go in the, in the, in the experience itself and, and to, to...
[SPEAKER_02]: To find out or to... through introspection.
[SPEAKER_02]: To inquire what's... how the human mind is...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's working, if I can say.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I would...
[SPEAKER_02]: What we were discussing before of the attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attitude, I would say, I would like to say,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... it's also important to see
[SPEAKER_02]: If someone comes to the dhamma as newcomer or also afterwards with an attitude of openness and saying
[SPEAKER_02]: I have my opinions, like everyone has, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I... do I have a...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a will to...
[SPEAKER_02]: to discuss or not to take what I have as opinion for granted and
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like this and... and remove it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or... or am I... am I...
[SPEAKER_02]: Available to hear others, to hear the noble ones who have the...
[SPEAKER_02]: This is a knowledge which has to be acquired.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think this is...
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, a very helpful point to recognize if...
[SPEAKER_02]: If we are able to let go a little bit of our preconceived opinions,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is about coming to terms with one's own views and assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when one adopts a scientific or academic or scholarly attitude, which is more or less the same,
[SPEAKER_01]: Can your own views and assumptions come to light if you take an objective stance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's about suffering, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it about my existential suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: address that to through the scientific or paradigm or scholarly attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole nature...
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of human existence, of personal existence, is fully outside the scope of the scientific domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we're not saying that there's anything wrong with science.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that the dhamma is outside of the phenomena that science investigates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And someone's own views and assumptions are not publicly observable.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example...
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, the whole practice begins, in a sense, by coming to terms with one's own views and assumptions about the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting them next to how the noble ones regard things, and then the question becomes, am I regarding things the way ordinary people do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, am I regarding things the way the noble ones do?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you find a discrepancy there, then the question is, why do you hold on
[SPEAKER_01]: to the way ordinary people regard things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that would be right, you wouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you wouldn't suffer, then what's the point of even reading the discourses?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a question of coming to terms with one's own view and, let's say, substituting those views for the right views that
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what is defining whether...
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude is authentic or not, is whether it pertains to suffering, and that's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a subjective reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: This Buddha kept all the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the Buddha would have been a scientist, he would never have become the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: He kept asking himself, am I still liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: If this happens, if that happens, then would that still affect my mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: When the answer is yes, there are still things that can disturb my mind, he would not declare full complete awakening.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a completely subjective reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that has to be established from the outset, because otherwise, one's whole frame of reference, as you put it, is just gonna be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, as you put it actually, it's going to be misinterpreted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's like, well, I interpret it like this, and I interpret it like that, but in the end...
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is seen individually by those who are wise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, there's no question of different interpretations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It either resolves the existential burden which is the dukkha, or it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, in addition to certain kinds of discourses that are worthwhile perhaps looking into first,
[SPEAKER_01]: What is of equal importance, or perhaps even more important, actually, is to approach the discourses with the right attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have said so far that the attitude is to not assume that one has understood what has not been understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: And secondly, to come to terms with one's own views and opinions and put them next
[SPEAKER_01]: To what one reads in the discourses, and then be honest with oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I regarding things the way the noble ones do, or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I still liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that is the attitude, and if somebody is transparent and honest,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, does it in the end really matter what kind of suttas they read?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, most of the bhikkhus, I mean, they didn't... No, none of the bhikkhus had access to the nikayas.
[SPEAKER_00]: During the time of the Buddha, I mean, they would have... many of them would have had, you know, only a few interactions with the Buddha or with his disciples, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's the other thing, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: The goal is not to read all the discourses or translate all of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, learn them all by heart, because, in fact, most people, even adults, it's not necessarily here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, it's better to fully understand and see all the implications of a few discourses
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, to have knowledge of all of them, but not see anything directly for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, how many discourses nowadays people need to reflect upon in order for the right view to land, will of course differ from individual to individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in a sense, it's a very rich situation that all the discourses are there, but we should not conflate
[SPEAKER_01]: Or a newcomer should not conflate the idea that it is about accumulating knowledge, because that's just more desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about actually understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the original question and the answers that are recorded in those discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if we have said all of this to a newcomer, right, to somebody who comes here and says where to begin with the discourses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then have we come up with a sufficient answer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is there anything more that we should say?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe, hear the discourses or read the discourses is one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But also, hearing the dhamma from
[SPEAKER_02]: From someone in which one can have a confidence,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's also very, very helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe watching, yes, watching some
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_02]: Leaving people, speaking about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: can also help, yeah, in addiction of... in...
[SPEAKER_02]: More, or how can I say, complementary to reading the texts and...
[SPEAKER_02]: And just, eh, come into terms with them by, by oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because texts don't speak back to you and they don't say whether you've interpreted them rightly or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there's perhaps a third category of discourses that we can briefly mention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: In addition to the ones where somebody breaks the dhamma and that stock phrase that contrasts ordinary people with the noble ones,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's also a collection of discourses where the factors for the arising of the right view are being discussed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if gaining the right view is the most important thing that a newcomer should look out for,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, to be aware of what the factors for the arising of right view are, is obviously of key importance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: And one of the factors for a right view is hearing true dhamma, which obviously means that if somebody is talking about it, they are ipso facto a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one needs to attend to those teachings rightly, which is the yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that deserves a whole separate discussion, so I suggest we don't go into that just now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those are the two factors for the arising of right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is sometimes further elaborated upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying that, you know, to hang out with those people who are already of right view is greatly beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, if somebody has no knowledge of the discourses, how are they ever going to recognize whether somebody else is presenting the Buddhist teaching rightly?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, that's going to be a difficulty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if one wants to follow someone else out of faith,
[SPEAKER_01]: I would still say that it is better to also make an effort to become familiar with the Pāṇikāyas
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to make sure that you're putting, that you're placing your faith rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're following someone who doesn't know what they're talking about, then you can basically spend the rest of your life practicing things that do not bring right results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you cannot start blaming the other person, because you were the one who decided to put your face there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you say?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's... sometimes it seems to me it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's really also... really, it's also a kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's a kind of... how can I say... it's not easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can one be sure
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, following this, this interpretation, I, I will, yes, I will go the way
[SPEAKER_02]: Which I will afterwards, after having explored and investigated, find the right or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you say about reading, learning the Pali?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I didn't say learning the Pāli, I said reading the Pāli.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reading the Pāli.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which can be in a translation, which... Ah, okay, yeah, you do the sūtās.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you do the sūtās.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, what then to look for in someone else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do the discourses say anything about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are there qualities that give at least some indication that someone might know what they're talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Perhaps we can conclude our discussion by clearing that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there are some indications like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: One doesn't really know whether somebody else has it, until...
[SPEAKER_01]: You yourself have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even then, there were discourses where arahants don't recognize other arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: But okay, being an arahant, that's not really an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, so how are you going to recognize that somebody else knows what they're talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we come up with some indications, some things that at least point in the right direction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it always has to be rooted in this authenticity that we talked about and responsibility in terms of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, am I liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: And is this
[SPEAKER_00]: Helping me to come out of my liability to suffering is this teaching helping me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without that authenticity, then...
[SPEAKER_00]: That is... yeah, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's so easy to follow somebody because they're charismatic, or they look confident, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's so many other people following them, for all sorts of reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this criteria of, am I suffering, or am I liable to suffering, is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Is what the Buddha was pointing to, or what his entire teaching is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so following someone's instruction and then checking for oneself, where the one's suffering diminishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you can see if you're moving in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you see, we are still talking one step back, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Where to put your faith?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody doesn't even observe, let's say, five or eight precepts, is it worthwhile listening to someone like that?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, good, good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Point two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, what is always said to
[SPEAKER_02]: To start with the sīla, with the restraints, but there also...
[SPEAKER_02]: It needs some understanding to, to, to make a reason why, why is this a, let's say, a prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, that understanding can follow, but that's of course never going to happen if you are listening to someone who himself or herself doesn't even follow these basic precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is seclusion a factor?
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody's always surrounded by other people?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that a good indication or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's also criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, as the suttas say, you have to get to know someone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, on a personal, intimate level, that's not always meant, but it takes, for this authentic attitude that you are referring to,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not so easy to discern if you just meet someone for the first time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it takes some time with someone or to regularly see someone in...
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to find out if you can catch a glimpse of that attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just once or twice or in public occasions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we see so often then behind the scene, you know, all the scandals and the misdemeanors come
[SPEAKER_01]: But publicly, it can all look great.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, one wants to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Careful with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we're talking about precepts, sense restraint, seclusion, and look for an attitude of authenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Honesty and people themselves being serious about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And perhaps...
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is up to the individual and to resolve their own doubts, which are going to be there anyway, until they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's a... that could be misleading, in the sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean subjectively, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does a noble disciple have doubt about what is dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, since the whole goal is to see dhamma,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there will always be doubts.
[SPEAKER_01]: About what dhamma is and what dhamma is not, and whether somebody else is perhaps speaking in accordance with dhamma or not, until one sees for oneself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if you need something else?
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, I just, yeah, no, it just maybe could have been interpreted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the doubt is something that one could, in a way,
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what you meant, obviously, when you disqualified it by saying...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the attitude towards doubt and... yeah, it's too...
[SPEAKER_00]: See it as doubt, and not to get absorbed in the content of the doubt, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aha, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: To recognize doubt as a phenomena will be necessary in order to abandon doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will be, in the end, up to the individual practitioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not going to be external circumstances resolving that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will already be part of looking at one's own mind and taking one's whole attitude subjectively.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would be careful with the word introspection, by the way, which you used earlier.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think I would use it like that, but to keep the subjective perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to realize that doubt is also part of suffering, and that it is an aspect of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Or seeing things rightly, that there can't be any doubt about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: One other thing that I find interesting to look for in perspective teacher is
[SPEAKER_03]: Their emphasis on personal responsibility...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, is this teacher somebody who is trying to teach you how to be independent of them?
[SPEAKER_03]: A good teacher doesn't want their students to call them up every time they have a question.
[SPEAKER_03]: A good teacher wants to teach the material so that the students can become independent in their understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so a noble disciple is independent of others in his understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a teacher is setting himself up in a way that students only become more dependent,
[SPEAKER_01]: On his teaching, or his organization, or his methods or technique, that should already be a big red flag.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's another factor for advice.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are no secret stages?
[SPEAKER_01]: There are no secrets?
[SPEAKER_02]: No secret stages in the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, there's no secrecy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's now the other thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: people who want to belong to something special, to something exclusive, that they might be drawn in.
[SPEAKER_01]: by taking special vows and do preliminary practices and become part of something secret or esoteric.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any such aspect in the early Buddhist teaching?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha himself explicitly said that there's nothing held back.
[SPEAKER_01]: in the closed fist of the teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the dhamma, from that point of view, is
[SPEAKER_01]: This doesn't mean publicly observable, but it is apparent here and now and accessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anyone who says, join my secret club,
[SPEAKER_01]: Should be another big bad flag.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any other factors?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think...
[SPEAKER_00]: Going back to the suttas, they have a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Consistent framework or context or understanding of all the suttas, that every single sutta
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like one sutta is saying one thing and the other sutta is saying another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there is this consistent understanding which enables...
[SPEAKER_00]: Every sutta to be easily understood, in the sense that it's effortless, because they abide in this understanding that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Incorporates all the suttas, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Incorporates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dhamma is not patchwork.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, we've got some people who have understood this collection of discourses, but there's a separate sect.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those kind of discourses were saying that dhamma is one vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, somebody should be capable of at least pointing out
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can put it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which all the discourses have in common, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so they might never have heard certain words, but then, if it's explained to them, they're like, oh, yeah, that's what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like they have this sort of etymological...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, knowledge or information, they just have this understanding which enables them to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it's about the meaning and not just about the phrasing, even though phrasing plays its part.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're not going to have quarrels back and forth about phrasing and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's important that somebody can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's what all discourses have in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering and the
[SPEAKER_01]: Ending of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody has that reference point...
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it doesn't really matter which suttas they begin with, in the end, if their attitude is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, every discourse should point in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Might do so to different degrees, or it might stop a bit earlier and doesn't go all the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they should all go in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what one wants to become familiar with.
[SPEAKER_01]: With that direction where suffering ceases, and then to just work on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.